Glasgow, UK

□ (+44) 7514744121 | www.virtual-climate.com | 🗖 ruggieroguida | www.virtual-climate.com





Summary _

Ruggiero wants to change the way the built environment is designed and operated by advocating Performance Based Design. Supported by strong software knowledge and experience in the built environment Ruggiero provides quantified advice on buildings as well as master plans. Ruggiero has spent more than 20 years in sustainability and in particular in green buildings, from concept to construction to operation. Currently he is working at IES Limited as Chief Product Manager for the Intelligent Communities Lifecycle. He focuses on urban modelling, building operations and outdoor comfort. Prior to IES he was an associate at WSP Middle East; building specialist at Sefaira, a green building software startup (now Trimble); and a Partner at London based Max Fordham?s LLP. Ruggiero holds a Master's degree in Mechanical Engineering and Computational Fluid Dynamics. He is a UK Chartered Engineer and member of CIBSE.

Work Experience

IES Ltd. Glasgow, UK

ASSOCIATE DIRECTOR - CHIEF PRODUCT MANAGER

Oct. 2016 - Present

- Transformed a series of disparate products in a cohesive software solution
- Coordinated various development efforts in one single enterprse solution
- Developed product vision together with the CEO
- Lead the UI/UX design team to develop a consistent design language across the product line
- Cloud evangelist Instrumental in company (on going) transition to cloud and SaaS
- Product managed several R&D software projects
- Support Marketing and Sales in presentations, demos and communication of product vision to existing and prospective customers
- Defining projects scope, goals and deliverables to ensure alignment with overall company and product vision
- Product management for the Intelligent Community Lifecycle for the last 4 years. I have been involved in all the products specification and development as product manager.
- Main responsibilities include product specification, product strategy, implementation management, customers and stakeholders? liaisons.

PRODUCT MANAGER Oct. 2016 - Present

- Product managed several R&D software projects
- Supported Marketing and Sales in presentation, demos and communicating product visions to existing and prospective customers
- Gathered feedback from users and translated it in user stories
- Defining projects scope, goals and deliverables to ensure alignment with overall company and product vision
- Main responsibilities include product specification, product strategy, implementation management, customers and stakeholders? liaisons.
- Project Manager and engineering technical lead Digital twin for a new development in Nottingham. IES created an interactive platform that enables the Trent Basin community to visualise its energy data in real-time.
- Stirling Smart Hub The project began with a principle aim to create a centralised smart energy platform where the council could easily monitor and manage energy and renewables data for its property portfolio. Although the council had strong vision and commitment, they were struggling to find adequate tools to achieve their goal. This is where IES and their ICL Digital Twin technology were able to help.
- Project Manager and engineering technical lead. Managed a team of 6 developers

Virtual Climate Ltd. Glasgow, UK

CO-FOUNDER & SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Feb. 2020 - Present

- Developed a desktop application in Ruby/Python/C with web frontend in HTML/Javascript for analysis of comfort conditions in outdoor spaces. The application solves complex Computational Fluid Dynamic on AWS Cluster. It uses a few AWS services such EC2, S3, EFS all via APIs.
- Together with my confounder I have used the application in various project in the Middle East and Europe
- Responsible for technical support and software development

Sabbatical Asia, South America, US

BUILDING PHYSICS AND SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

• I spent one year travelling and developing what has now become MCTools.

• Used the year to develop a more robust code base from the side project started during my time in Dubo

WSP Middle East Dubai, UAE

ASSOCIATE Jan. 2012 -May. 2015

- Ruggiero's role was to oversee the building physics team within the Sustainability and Energy group. He focused on building physics and computer modeling of the built environment and promoted the integration of sustainability in the design process from the early stages through the use of technology.
- BVLGARI Island Dubai? CFD, Building Energy Modelling, Outdoor Comfort
- Opera District Dubai? Outdoor Comfort and Wind Analysis
- Development of Simulation Based Building Regulations in Philippines, Vietnam and Bangladesh in collaboration with International Finance Corporation (World Bank)

Sefaira (Now part of Trimble)

London, UK

PRINCIPAL BUILDING ENGINEER

Jul. 2010 - Dec. 2012

Jun. 2015 - Sep. 2016

- Reporting directly to the VP of engineering Ruggiero contributed to shape the software and advised architects on energy efficiency and passive design.
- I was employee number five in a new startup set to disrupt the early stage design of buildings.

Max Fordham London, UK

ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEER

Jun. 2005 - Jun. 2010

- Appointed initially as a Building Physicist, Ruggiero subsequently developed this role to become a key figure in the modelling department of the company. This role enabled him to develop his design skills, with the final promotion as Project Engineer in 2008 and Partner in 2009.
- Involved with different roles in various prestigious projects such as the London Olympics Waterpolo Arena, several Zaha Hadid buildings
- Main roles and responsibility were building physics, mechanical design and project management
- Key skils: building energy modelling, computational fluid dynamics, mechanical design

Certifications & Awards

2015 Winner, Middle East Green Building Research award

Dubai, UAE

2011 Member, CIBSE - Chartered Institution of Building Service Engineers

UK

Education

Politecnico di Bari Italy

M.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING AND COMPUTATIONAL FLUID DYNAMICS

1993 - 2000

• Spent a year in Manchester at Manchester Metropolitan University to write thesis

Skills

Programming Ruby (Intermediate), Python (Basic), , Rancher, Vagrant, Packer, Terraform, Jenkins, CircleCl

Basic Knowledge Python, C, Javascript, HTML

Hobby Electronics, IoT, Non Fiction Reading

Product Management Agile methodologies, Scrum, demos, users interview

Soft Skills Client liaison, Presentations, Team Engagement **Management** Mentoring, Tutoring, Project Management, support

Languages Italian, English

September 24, 2021 Glasgow · Résumé 2